<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><record_update table="sp_widget">
    <sp_widget action="INSERT_OR_UPDATE">
        <category>custom</category>
        <client_script><![CDATA[function($scope, $location) {
  /* widget controller */
	var c = this;
	var url = "https://www.citizensinformation.ie/en/employment/return_to_work/returning_to_work_and_covid19.html";

	
	$scope.iframeUrl = url;
}]]></client_script>
        <controller_as>c</controller_as>
        <css>.frame-style {&#13;
	height: 100%;&#13;
  width: 100%;&#13;
  border: 0px;&#13;
}&#13;
</css>
        <data_table>sp_instance</data_table>
        <demo_data/>
        <description/>
        <docs/>
        <field_list/>
        <has_preview>true</has_preview>
        <id/>
        <internal>false</internal>
        <link><![CDATA[function(scope, elem, attrs) {
	var panelHeight;

	$(document).ready(function() {
		resizeWindow();
	});

	$(window).resize(function() {
		resizeWindow();
	});

	function resizeWindow() {
		var panelHeight = ($(document).height()- 60) + 'px';
		$(elem).find('#pwd_reset_container').css('height', panelHeight);
	}
}]]></link>
        <name>Covid 19 Info</name>
        <option_schema/>
        <public>true</public>
        <roles/>
        <script><![CDATA[(function() {
  /* populate the 'data' object */
  /* e.g., data.table = $sp.getValue('table'); */

})();]]></script>
        <servicenow>false</servicenow>
        <sys_class_name>sp_widget</sys_class_name>
        <sys_created_by>admin</sys_created_by>
        <sys_created_on>2021-10-23 17:05:26</sys_created_on>
        <sys_id>0e6f43f22fdf301091f2fcecf699b6ab</sys_id>
        <sys_mod_count>5</sys_mod_count>
        <sys_name>Covid 19 Info</sys_name>
        <sys_package display_value="Return to Workplace" source="x_94093_return_to">7c3d5ee22f13301091f2fcecf699b60b</sys_package>
        <sys_policy/>
        <sys_scope display_value="Return to Workplace">7c3d5ee22f13301091f2fcecf699b60b</sys_scope>
        <sys_update_name>sp_widget_0e6f43f22fdf301091f2fcecf699b6ab</sys_update_name>
        <sys_updated_by>admin</sys_updated_by>
        <sys_updated_on>2021-10-23 17:12:03</sys_updated_on>
        <template><![CDATA[<div class="content" role="main">
                
                
<!-- Bread crumb -->


<!--end of breadcrumbs-->
                

                <!-- start of Document -->
                <a id="startcontent"></a>

                
                
                <h1>Returning to working safely</h1>
                
                


                
    <ul class="anchorlinks"><li><a href="#l0b797">Introduction</a></li><li><a href="#lb74e9">Return to the workplace </a></li><li><a href="#l17a59">Planning for return to work</a></li><li><a href="#l01e6d">Getting to and from work</a></li><li><a href="#l3b81c">Staying safe at work</a></li><li><a href="#l9eb00">Where can I make a complaint?</a></li><li><a href="#l23f7d">Further information</a></li></ul>
    <div class="topic">

<div class="topic base_introduction">
<h2 class="topic base_introduction_title" id="l0b797">Introduction</h2>

<p>Workers still working from home can return to the workplace on a phased and
staggered basis. <strong>Attendance should be for specific business needs
only</strong>. This restriction remains in place, even after 22 October 2021.
</p>

<h3>Guidance for employers on the return to work</h3>

<p>This page summarises the work safely protocol published by the HSA, the HSE,
the Department of Health and the Department of Enterprise, Trade and
Employment. </p>

<p>Further guidance and an updated work safely protocol were issued in
September 2021 ahead of the Government advice on the phased return to
workplaces.</p>

<p>Employers must review their existing advice and guidance to make sure it is
in line with the updated guidance.</p>

<p>The protocol and related guidance:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Describes the steps that employers and employees should take before a
    workplace reopens to make sure they can return to work safely</li>
  <li>Sets out the minimum measures needed in every workplace to manage and
    prevent the spread of infection.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can get more detailed information in the revised <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">Work
Safely Protocol (pdf)</a> and the <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Returning-Safely-to-the-Workplace.pdf">Guidance
Note on Returning Safely to the Workplace (pdf)</a>.</p>

<p>The protocol gives information on the selection of hand sanitisers, the
wearing of face coverings, working from home, the use of antigen testing,
vaccinations and ventilation of workplaces. There may be additional safeguards
in different workplaces.</p>

<p>The additional guidance gives information on the use of staggered
arrangements and other considerations around attendance levels.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/topics/covid-19_coronavirus_information_and_resources/covid-19_business_supports/business_supports/work_safely_templates_checklists_and_posters/">Health
Safety Authority (HSA) website</a> has updated checklists and templates on
ventilation, rapid antigen testing and returning to the office.</p>

<p>The HSA will carry out workplace inspections and provide guidance for
employers. If their advice is not implemented, the HSA can shut down the
workplace.</p>

<p>The Workplace Relations Commission (WRC) will also carry out inspections and
provide guidance to employers.</p>
</div>

<div class="topic base_introduction">
<h2 class="topic base_introduction_title" id="lb74e9">Return to the workplace </h2>

<p>Workers still working from home can return to the workplace on a phased and
cautious basis.</p>

<p>The return to workplace must be managed in a cautious and careful way.
<strong>Attendance should be for specific business needs only</strong>.</p>

<p>The updated <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Returning-Safely-to-the-Workplace.pdf">Guidance
Note on Returning Safely to the Workplace (pdf)</a> recommends that employers
consider:</p>
<ul>
  <li>That attendance is for specific business requirements </li>
  <li>Appropriate attendance levels, keeping in mind the work safely protocol
    and related checklists</li>
  <li>Using staggered arrangements, for example flexible working hours and
    part-time attendance</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="topic base_introduction">
<h3>Return to the workplace after 22 October</h3>

<p>It had been planned that the requirement to work from home would be removed
after 22 October 2021. However, on 19 October 2021, it was announced that
workers should <a href="https://www.gov.ie/en/press-release/58d28-statement-on-covid-19-public-health-measures-19-october-2021/">only
attend the workplace for specific business requirements</a>. </p>
</div>

<div class="topic base_rules">
<h2 class="topic base_rules_title" id="l17a59">Planning for return to work</h2>

<p>All employers must prepare and put systems and controls in place before they
reopen their business and workplaces.</p>

<p>Your employer must:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Appoint at least <strong>one lead worker representative</strong> to make
    sure safety measures are in place and being followed. A short online course
    on the role of lead worker representative can be found on the <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/LWR/#/">HSA website</a>.</li>
  <li><strong>Update business and safety plans</strong>, including the business
    COVID-19 Response Plan, the occupational health and safety risk assessment
    and the safety statement. Include <strong>how to deal with a suspected case
    of COVID-19</strong> in the safety plans and appoint a dedicated manager in
    charge of dealing with suspected cases.</li>
  <li>Develop, consult on, communicate and implement workplace changes or
    policies.</li>
  <li>Provide <strong>COVID-19 induction training</strong> for all staff.</li>
  <li>Put in place <strong>temperature testing</strong> in line with public
    health advice.</li>
</ul>

<p>Any <strong>mass COVID-19 testing</strong> needed in line with public health
advice, must be on <strong>a voluntary basis</strong>. Employers must put an
agreed process in place for staff who do not want to take part in the testing-
see 'Antigen testing in the workplace' below.</p>

<h3>Pre-return to work form</h3>

<p>An employer must send out a pre-return to work form to employees before
their return to work.</p>
<ul>
  <li>The employee must submit the form before they return to work.</li>
  <li>The form will ask employees to confirm they have not had <a href="https://www2.hse.ie/conditions/coronavirus/symptoms.html">symptoms of
    COVID-19</a> in the past 14 days, have not been diagnosed or suspected of
    COVID-19 in the past 14 days, have not been in close contact with someone
    confirmed or suspected of COVID-19 in the past 14 days and are not <a href="../../health/covid19/covid19_isolation_and_restricting.en.html">restricting
    their movements or self-isolating</a>.</li>
  <li>You can get a <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/topics/covid-19_coronavirus_information_and_resources/covid-19_business_supports/business_supports/work_safely_templates_checklists_and_posters/">return
    to work form template</a> from the HSA website. </li>
</ul>

<p>Completed forms should only be kept for as long as necessary by the employer
and in line with the advice from the <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Data-Protection-Work-Safely-Protocol.html">Data
Protection Commission</a>.</p>

<h3>Antigen testing in the workplace </h3>

<p>Rapid Antigen Diagnostic Tests (RADTs) can detect the presence or absence of
specific antigens or proteins on the surface of the virus.</p>

<p>Your employer can, with your agreement, implement additional checks by
setting up a RADT testing regime.</p>

<p>Your employer must:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Discuss and agree the implementation of a testing regime with you, the
    lead workers representative, the safety representative and the union (if
    there is one)</li>
  <li>Agree a process for workers who do not want to take part in the RADT
    testing</li>
  <li>Update the COVID-19 Response plan and any other policies and procedure to
    take account of the agreed testing policy</li>
  <li>Provide training for all staff who are engaged in the RADT testing, so
    you can undertake the test safely and correctly</li>
  <li>Agree clear protocols for managing positive cases</li>
</ul>

<p>Any employer who is setting up an RADT testing regime, should consult the
detailed guidance in <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">section
D13 of the Work Safely Protocol (pdf)</a>. </p>

<p>Employers must make sure that public health advice regarding hand washing,
mask wearing, respiratory etiquette, physical distancing and ventilation are
still fully adhered to in the workplace.</p>

<p>You can get more information on RADTs in <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">Appendix
F of the protocol (pdf)</a>, on the <a href="https://www.hpra.ie/homepage/medical-devices/covid-19-updates/in-vitro-diagnostic-(ivd)-tests-for-covid-19">Health
Products Regulatory Authority website</a> and <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/topics/covid-19_coronavirus_information_and_resources/covid-19_business_supports/business_supports/work_safely_templates_checklists_and_posters/employers-checklist-no-10---radts--12-aug-2021.pdf">Checklist
No. 10 on RADTs (pdf)</a>.</p>

<p>If an employee is has symptoms of COVID-19, they should phone their GP or <a href="https://www2.hse.ie/conditions/covid19/testing/get-tested/">book a PCR
test on the HSE website</a> as soon as possible.</p>

<h3>Vaccinations</h3>

<p>The decision to get a vaccination against COVID-19 <strong>is
voluntary</strong>. Therefore you can make your own decision about whether or
not to get a vaccination.</p>

<p>Your employer may provide you with advice and information on the vaccination
programme so that you have the necessary information to make an informed
decision.</p>

<p><strong>Telling your employer your vaccination status</strong></p>

<p>In most cases, you do not have to tell your employer whether or not you are
vaccinated. Guidance from the Data Protection Commission states that, in
general, there is no legal basis to collect or process an employee's
vaccination data.</p>

<h4>Workplace exposure to COVID-19</h4>

<p>In some workplaces, exposure to COVID-19 may be a health risk to workers,
for example workers in laboratory settings. In this case, an employer must
complete a risk assessment and implement suitable control measures. Your
employer can offer you a vaccination but you do not have to accept the
offer.</p>

<p>If you decide not to accept the offer of a vaccination, your employer must
review their risk assessment and decide whether you can carry out your work
without vaccination, and what other protective measures are needed. In some
cases, your employer may have no option but to redeploy you to another task or
role. Your employer must agree this with a medical practitioner and you must be
consulted.</p>

<p>You can get more detailed guidance on vaccinations in <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">section
D14 of the Work Safely Protocol (pdf)</a>.</p>
</div>

<div class="topic base_rates">
<h2 class="topic base_rates_title" id="l01e6d">Getting to and from work</h2>

<p>You should follow public health advice and keep to physical distancing
guidelines if using your personal car for work. Where sharing a car with a
co-worker, a face covering should be worn. Your employer should give you hand
sanitisers and cleaning equipment for your work vehicle.</p>

<p>You should keep windows in your work vehicle open, or partially open.
Vehicle heating and ventilation systems should not be set to recirculate air.
</p>

<p>Walk or cycle where possible.</p>

<p>If you are using public transport, you must <a href="https://www.citizensinformation.ie/en/health/covid19/face_coverings_during_covid19.html">wear
a face covering</a>.</p>
</div>

<div class="topic base_howtoapply">
<h2 class="topic base_howtoapply_title" id="l3b81c">Staying safe at work</h2>

<p>Employers and employees should work together to help reduce the spread of
COVID-19 and know the symptoms of COVID-19. The complete <a href="https://www2.hse.ie/conditions/coronavirus/symptoms.html">list of
COVID-19 symptoms</a> is available on the HSE Website.</p>

<h3>Employer's responsibilities </h3>

<p>Your employer must:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Have appropriate <strong>hygiene facilities</strong> readily available,
    display posters of <a href="https://www2.hse.ie/wellbeing/how-to-wash-your-hands.html">good hand
    washing practices</a> and have adequate ventilation for example open doors
    and windows.</li>
  <li>Give tissues as well as bins or bags for employee's disposal. </li>
  <li>Empty bins regularly and provide advice on <strong>good respiratory
    practice</strong>, including the safe use, storage and disposal of face
    masks<strong>.</strong><strong></strong></li>
  <li>Provide for <strong>physical distancing</strong> across all work
    activities of at least 2 metres as much as possible. (Staggering breaks, or
    place teams in pods, put in place arrangements for meetings and canteen
    facilities, put in place a no handshaking policy, no sharing of cups or
    pens, adapt sign in or sign out systems). Install physical barriers, such
    as clear plastic sneeze guards between workers were 2 metre distancing is
    not possible. </li>
  <li><strong>Keep a log of contacts</strong> to help with contact tracing.</li>
  <li><strong>Have regular cleaning</strong> of the workplace and provide hand
    sanitisers. An alcohol based sanitiser must have a minimum of 60% alcohol.
    See the <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">Work
    Safely Protocol (pdf)</a> for more details on cleaning and advice on
    choosing a hand sanitiser. </li>
  <li>Provide <strong>Personal Protective Equipment (PPE)</strong> and
    protective clothing where there is an identified COVID-19 exposure risk and
    in line with public health advice. You <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/Topics/Personal_Protective_Equipment_-_PPE/">can
    get more information on PPE from the HSA.</a></li>
  <li>Make sure employees look after their <strong>mental health and
    well-being</strong> and are aware of any employee assistance programmes.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>If an employee has symptoms of COVID-19</h3>

<p>If an employee has symptoms of the virus during work hours, your employer
must have a designated isolation area for employees and must follow a specific
procedure:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The designated manager must direct the person to a designated isolation
    area, along a designated route (make provisions for one or more persons
    displaying symptoms such as an additional isolation area or have
    contingency plans in place) </li>
  <li>Maintain a 2 metre distance</li>
  <li>Provide a face mask for the person presenting with symptoms. The worker
    should wear the mask if in a common area with other people or while exiting
    the premises</li>
  <li>Arrange for the employee to stay in isolation before arranging for them
    to be transported home, or to a medical facility, public transport should
    not be used.</li>
  <li>Arrange for appropriate cleaning of the isolation area and work areas</li>
  <li>Carry out a full risk assessment of the incident to see what, if any,
    further action needs to be taken</li>
</ul>

<h3>Employee's responsibilities</h3>

<p>As an employee, you should:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Follow the public health advice and guidance</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Work together with your employer</strong> and follow any specific
    procedures and instructions from your employer to keep safe</li>
  <li><strong>Undergo any voluntary mass COVID-19 testing</strong> (if you
    agree to this) needed in line with public health advice – see 'Antigen
    testing in the workplace' above</li>
  <li>Adopt <strong>good hygiene practices</strong>, such as frequent hand
    washing, respiratory etiquette and physical distancing</li>
  <li>Get professional healthcare advice if you are unwell</li>
  <li>Not go to work if you have any symptoms of COVID-19, and get a test as
    soon as possible</li>
  <li>Let your employer know if you believe there are reasons why it is not
    safe for you to be at work, or if you are concerned that you could be
    putting a member of your household at risk</li>
  <li>Undertake a medical risk assessment with an Occupational Health
    practitioner or your GP before returning to work, if you are in the very
    high risk (extremely vulnerable) category</li>
  <li>Wear a face covering in specific areas of the office, where physical
    distancing is difficult</li>
  <li>If identified as a close contact of a confirmed case of COVID-19, <a href="https://www2.hse.ie/conditions/covid19/contact-tracing/close-contact/">follow
    the close contact advice on the HSE website</a></li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="topic base_howtoapply">
<h2 class="topic base_howtoapply_title" id="l9eb00">Where can I make a complaint?</h2>
The Health and Safety Authority is responsible for making sure businesses
comply with the Work Safely Protocol. If you feel your employer is not meeting
the standards in this protocol you can raise their concerns with the HSA. The
HSA will address the concerns with your employer. 

<p>You can make a complaint using the HSA's <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/publications_and_forms/online_complaint_form/online_complaint_form.html">online
complaint form</a>. You should raise your concern with your employer first to
give them a chance to fix the issue. </p>
</div>

<div class="topic base_wheretoapply">
<h2 class="topic base_wheretoapply_title" id="l23f7d">Further information</h2>

<p>Everyone should stay safe and make themselves aware of the advice in the <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Work-Safely-Protocol.pdf">work
safely protocol (pdf)</a> and the <a href="https://enterprise.gov.ie/en/Publications/Publication-files/Returning-Safely-to-the-Workplace.pdf">Guidance
Note on Returning Safely to the Workplace from 20 September (pdf)</a>.</p>

<p>Employers can get <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/topics/covid-19_coronavirus_information_and_resources/covid-19_business_supports/business_supports/work_safely_templates_checklists_and_posters/" name="return" id="return">return to work COVID-19 templates and checklists</a>
from the HSA and <a href="https://www.hse.ie/eng/services/news/newsfeatures/covid19-updates/partner-resources/">COVID-19
posters and signs</a> from the HSE. The HSA also have <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/topics/covid-19_coronavirus_information_and_resources/covid-19_business_supports/business_supports/work_safely_online_courses/">return
to work safely online courses</a>. </p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.skillnetireland.ie/rebound/">Skillnet Ireland
ReBound</a> initiative gives small businesses online training and mentoring on
implementing the return to work safely protocol.</p>

<p>Employers can get information on the <a href="../types_of_employment/self_employment/supports_for_businesses_covid19.en.html">financial
supports</a> and business advice available to help with their cash flow,
payroll and long-term investments. </p>

<p>The National Standards Authority of Ireland (NSAI) has <a href="https://www.nsai.ie/covid-19/">COVID-19 Business Continuity Guides and
technical resources</a>.</p>

<p></p>
</div>

<div class="sharedaddress">
    <h3>Health and Safety Authority</h3>

    

    
    <p>The Metropolitan Building<br>James Joyce Street<br>Dublin 1<br>D01 K0Y8</p>
    

    
    <div><b>Opening Hours:</b> Lines are open on Monday to Fridays 9am - 3pm</div>
    

    
    <div><b>Tel:</b> (01) 614 7000</div>
    

    
    <div><b>Locall:</b> 1890 28 93 89</div>
    

    
    <div><b>Fax:</b> (01) 614 7020</div>
    

    
    <div><b>Homepage:</b> <a href="https://www.hsa.ie">https://www.hsa.ie</a></div>
    

    

    
    <div><b>Contact Form:</b> <a href="https://www.hsa.ie/eng/Contact_Us/">https://www.hsa.ie/eng/Contact_Us/</a></div>
    

    
    <div><b>Email:</b> <a href="mailto:wcu@hsa.ie">wcu@hsa.ie</a></div>
    

</div>

</div>


    
    <style>
        #lastupdated {
            margin-top: 20px;
        }
    </style>
    <div id="lastupdated">
        <em>
            <b>Page edited:</b>
            22 October 2021
        </em>
    </div>


    <div role="region" aria-label="Sharing buttons for social media">

    


</div>




                <!-- New cookie code -->
                
                
                <!-- New cookie code -->

                
                


                <div class="clear"></div>

            </div>]]></template>
    </sp_widget>
</record_update>
